<chapter>
	<title>Elements and Attributes</title>
	<section>
		<title>Required or Optional Elements and Attributes</title>
		<para>
			Information about "required" or "optional" elements and
			attributes can be found in the corresponding XSDs.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Predecessor(s)/Successor(s)</title>
		<para>
			An Organizational Unit can have one or more predecessors which
			is to reflect through predecessor elements. Please use
			organizational-unit.xsd as parameter reference.
		</para>
		<para>A predecessors relation is created and updated by pointing from
			a Organizational Unit to it predecessor. Each Organizational Unit has
			as virtual resource an XML representation of the backwards relation.
			This relation --from predecessors to the successor-- is automatically
			managed by the framework and is not directly alterable.
		</para>
		<para>
			Different scenarios define predecessor relations. The kind of
			scenario is reflected through the attribute &quot;form&quot;. 
			Depending on predecessor form can an Organizational Unit have exactly 
			one or multiple predecessors.
			
			It is required to define the form of predecessor relation. Each form is 
			coevally combined with a set of rules to prevent wrong relations. 
		</para>
				<para>
			Following types of predecessor relations are defined:    
			<itemizedlist mark="predecessor_forms">
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis role="bold">fusion</emphasis>
							Use &quot;fusion&quot; as from if the new Organizational Unit is founded 
							by a fusion of it's predecessors. This means simultaneously 
							that at least two predecessors has to exist. All predecessors 
							should be closed (real Organizations usually not exists as 
							separate Organization after a fusion and should therefore be
							in status closed).     
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis role="bold">replacement</emphasis>
							A &quot;replacement&quot; is to use if the Organizational Unit 
							follows directly from one predecessor and the 
							predecessor not exists any longer. Using replacement as 
							predecessor form means also that only one predecessor relation 
							can exists. The predecessor should have status closed.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis role="bold">splitting</emphasis>
							A &quot;splitting&quot; is to use if an Organizational Unit has more than one 
							successor. The predecessor itself not longer exists. This form 
							reflects a splitting of an Organizational Units into multiple new 
							Organizational Units (e.g. each former department of an 
							Organizational Unit without own	id and representation is to 
							defined as separate Organizational Unit).  
							A predecessor relation with form &quot;splitting&quot; can only consist 
							of one relation. The predecessor should have status closed.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis role="bold">spin-off</emphasis>
							A &quot;spin-off&quot; is to use if an department of an Organizational Unit is
							founded as new separate Organizational Unit and the predecessor 
							is still active (with the rest of the departments). Only one predecessor
							relation with form &quot;spin-off&quot; is allowed. 
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis role="bold">affiliation</emphasis>
							A &quot;affiliation&quot; is to use if an independent Organizational Unit is
							going to be part of another already existing Organizational Unit.
							The predecessor, the affiliated Organizational Unit, not exists as 
							separate Organization afterwards. Only one predecessor
							relation with form &quot;affiliation&quot; is allowed. 
					</para>
				</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</para>		
		<para>
			Predecessor elements are
			set or updated with an update of the
			whole Organizational Unit XML
			representation. A special method for
			this values is not supported.
		</para>
		<para>
		The following snippet give an example how predecessors with form &quot;fusion&quot; 
		are to define.  
		<programlisting>
			&lt;predecessors&gt;
			&lt;predecessor form=&quot;fusion&quot; xlink:href=&quot;/oum/organizational-unit/escidoc:123&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;predecessor form=&quot;fusion&quot; xlink:href=&quot;/oum/organizational-unit/escidoc:124&quot; /&gt;
			&lt;/predecessors&gt;
		</programlisting>
		</para>
	</section>

</chapter>