<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <title>Methods for SOAP Interface</title>

  <section>
    <title>Explain</title>

    <table>
      <title>Explain via SOAP</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Service</entry>

            <entry>ExplainPort</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Method Signature</entry>

            <entry>ExplainPort.explainOperation</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Parameter</entry>

            <entry>ExplainRequestType-Object</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Output</entry>

            <entry>ExplainResponseType-Object (explain-plan as
            java-object)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Possible errors</entry>

            <entry>RemoteException</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Search</title>

    <para>For searching, the SRW Server gets called with the url of the
    database and additional request parameters.</para>

    <table>
      <title>Request parameters</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>query (M)</entry>

            <entry>Contains a query expressed in CQL to be processed by the
            server (see
            http://www.loc.gov/standards/sru/cql/index.html)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>startRecord</entry>

            <entry>The position within the sequence of matched records of the
            first record to be returned. The first position in the sequence is
            1. The value supplied must be greater than 0. Default value if not
            supplied is 1.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>maximumRecords</entry>

            <entry>The number of records requested to be returned. The value
            must be 0 or greater. Default value if not supplied is determined
            by the server (see explain plan). The server may return less than
            this number of records, for example if there are fewer matching
            records than requested.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>recordPacking</entry>

            <entry>A string to determine how the record should be escaped in
            the response. Defined values are 'string' and 'xml'. The default
            is 'xml'.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>recordSchema</entry>

            <entry>The schema requested for the records to be returned. See
            explain plan for supported record schemas</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>recordXPath</entry>

            <entry>Not supported by SRW Server</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>resultSetTTL</entry>

            <entry>The number of seconds for which the client requests that
            the result set created should be maintained. eSciDoc does not
            maintain resultSets because of problems with the length of search
            results and the sorting mechanism that might result in performance
            problems. It certainly is possible to retrieve subsequent pages of
            the same search result. In this case, search is executed once
            again. </entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>sortKeys</entry>

            <entry>Contains a sequence of sort keys to be applied to the
            results. See explain plan for sort keys.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>stylesheet</entry>

            <entry>A URL for an xml stylesheet. The client requests that the
            server simply return this URL in the response. The
            stylesheet-parameter just gets returned with the response as
            header and triggers a stylesheet-conversion at the client-side (ie
            the browser of the user).</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>Result of the search is a list of search records in the requested
    schema. For the 1st Release, eSciDoc only supports the eSciDoc default
    schema for search results.</para>

    <para>The default record for search results contains the link to the
    object in eSciDoc, all metadata and properties, information about the
    components that belog to the object and a text snippet that shows in which
    context the hit was found. (see example result in attached file
    searchResult.xml).</para>

    <para>Only released objects get indexed, so the search can only find
    released objects!</para>

    <para>All components of the item are searchable, even if they are not
    publicly visible!</para>

    <table>
      <title>Search via SOAP</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Service</entry>

            <entry>SRWPort</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Method Signature</entry>

            <entry>SRWPort.searchRetrieveOperation</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Parameter</entry>

            <entry>SearchRetrieveRequestType-Object</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Output</entry>

            <entry>SearchRetrieveResponseType-Object</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Possible errors</entry>

            <entry><para>Different errors of Diagnostics Type (also contained
            in SearchRetrieveResponseType-Object). </para><para>For list of
            possible diagnostics, see
            http://www.loc.gov/standards/sru/diagnostics-list.html</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Scan</title>

    <para>While the searchRetrieve operation enables searches for a specific
    term within a list of indexed terms from the records, the scan operation
    allows the client to request a range of the available terms at a given
    point within that list. This enables clients to present an ordered list of
    values and, if supported, how many hits there would be for a search on
    that term. Scan is often used to select terms for subsequent searching or
    to verify visually a negative search result.</para>

    <table>
      <title>Supported request-parameters</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>scanClause (M</entry>

            <entry>The index field to be browsed and the start point within
            it, expressed as a complete index-field, relation, term clause in
            CQL.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Operation (M)</entry>

            <entry>‘scan’</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>responsePosition</entry>

            <entry><para>The position within the list of terms returned where
            the client would like the start term to occur. If the position
            given is 0, then the term should be immediately before the first
            term in the response. If the position given is 1, then the term
            should be first in the list, and so forth up to the number of
            terms requested plus 1, meaning that the term should be
            immediately after the last term in the response, even if the
            number of terms returned is less than the number requested.
            </para><para>The range of values is 0 to the number of terms
            requested plus 1. The default value is 1. </para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>maximumTerms</entry>

            <entry><para>The number of terms which the client requests be
            returned. The actual number returned may be less than this, for
            example if the end of the term list is reached, but may not be
            more. The explain record for the database may indicate the maximum
            number of terms which the server will return at once.
            </para><para>All positive integers are valid for this parameter.
            If not specified, the default is server determined.</para></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>stylesheet</entry>

            <entry>A URL for an xml stylesheet. The client requests that the
            server simply returns this URL in the response.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <table>
      <title>Scan via SOAP</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Service</entry>

            <entry>SRWPort</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Method Signature</entry>

            <entry>SRWPort.scanOperation</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Parameter</entry>

            <entry>ScanRequestType-Object</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Output</entry>

            <entry>ScanResponseType-Object</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Possible errors</entry>

            <entry><para>Different errors of Diagnostics Type (also contained
            in ScanResponseType-Object). </para><para>For list of possible
            diagnostics, see
            http://www.loc.gov/standards/sru/diagnostics-list.html</para></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>
</chapter>