<chapter>
	<title>Resource UserAccount</title>
    <section>
        <title>General Information</title>
        <para> An eSciDoc UserAccount is a proxy object that represents an eSciDoc
            user. For each user, the name, loginname, email and the user's
            organizational unit can be stored. These data has to be provided by an
            external user management and will be updated by the user management
            wrapper when the user logs in to eSciDoc. As the external user
            management does not provide the password in general and may use other
            credentials than a password, no password of the user is managed within
            eSciDoc. </para>
        <para> The details about the data stored in an UserAccount can be found in
                section 5.2 . In addition to the noted
            information, the User Manager stores a temporarily valid
            eSciDocUserHandle that is used to identify the user during the
            authentication of incoming requests. This handle is not provided
            within the UserAccount but can be used to retrieve it. </para>
        <para> Furthermore, the identification of an existing UserAccount by
            using the data provided by the external user management has to be
            supported. This is needed by the UserManagementWrapper. As it cannot
            be generally guaranteed that the external management provides a
            loginname that is unique within eSciDoc or provides an email address,
            another unique key (besides the internal id, the loginname and the
            eSciDocHandle) is stored and used to identify an User within the
            UserManagementWrapper. This key may be generated e.g. by
            concatenating a provided loginname and the name of the user's
            affiliation, or by using another unique information within the
            provided data. For the first release, it is assumed that the external
            user management provides an email address, that is used to identify the
            User. </para>
        <para>User-Accounts can have user-attributes attached that can get created via the UserAccount-Interface
        or that are implicitly created when logging in via Shibboleth or LDAP.
        So it is possible to store the organizational-unit the user belongs to as user-attribute.
        The eSciDoc-core framework also can store hierarchies of organizational-units in the repository. 
        If the user belongs to one (or more) of the organizational-units that are stored within the eSciDocCore-framework
        it is possible to resolve the hierarchy of the organizational-units. 
        This is important if eg the member-users of a group are defined via a user-attribute-selector.
        User is member if he belongs to the organizational-unit defined in the selector or to one of its child organizational-units.
        To be able to resolve the hierarchy the framework has to know the name of the user-attribute containing the organizational-unit.
        This name is configurable and has the default-value 'o'. 
        So in default-configuration, all user-attributes with name 'o' are treated as organizational-units.
        It is important to store the unique escidoc-id of the 
        organizational-unit as value of the attribute and not the name of the organizational-unit!
        The default-configuration can get overwritten 
        by changing the property <cmdsynopsis><command>escidoc-core.aa.attribute-name.ou</command></cmdsynopsis>
        in the escidoc-core.properties file that is located in &lt;jboss-home&gt;/server/default/conf.
        </para>
        <para> Each user gets assigned a number of roles, which make up, what the user
            is allowed to do within eSciDoc. A role is granted to an user by adding a
            respective Grant (see below) object to the UserAccount. It stores
            information about the grante role and, in case of a limited role, for
            which object the role has been granted. These Grants are not provided
            within the UserAccount resource itself but are available as a
            (virtual) subresource of UserAccount.</para> <note>
            <para>Granting roles to a user for specific objects is limited to
                objects of the following resource types:</para>
            <itemizedlist mark="opencircle" spacing="compact">
                <listitem>
                    <para>container</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>content model</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>context</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>item</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>organizational unit</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>scope</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </note>
    </section>
	<section>
		<title>XML Schemas</title>
        <para> In all methods XML-data is used as input and output. The related
            XML-schemas are located in <itemizedlist mark="opencircle"
        spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
           <para>www.escidoc.de/schemas/rest/user-account/0.5</para> 
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
           <para>www.escidoc.de/schemas/soap/user-account/0.5</para> 
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Description of XML-Elements</title>
		<section >
			<title>UserAccount</title>
			<table frame="all">
				<title>Elements of User Account</title>
				<tgroup cols="17" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
					<colspec colname="c1" />
					<colspec colname="c2" />
					<colspec colname="c3" />
					<colspec colname="c4" />
					<colspec colname="c5" />
					<colspec colname="c6" />
					<colspec colname="c7" />
					<colspec colname="c8" />
					<colspec colname="c9" />
					<colspec colname="c10" />
					<colspec colname="c11" />
					<colspec colname="c12" />
					<colspec colname="c13" />
					<colspec colname="c14" />
					<colspec colname="c15" />
					<colspec colname="c16" />
					<colspec colname="c17" />
					<spanspec spanname="element" namest="c1"
						nameend="c4" align="left" />
					<spanspec spanname="desc" namest="c5" nameend="c17"
						align="left" />
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry spanname="element">Element</entry>

							<entry spanname="desc">Desription</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry spanname="element">objid</entry>

							<entry spanname="desc">
								An unique identifier of the UserAccount
								within the system. This id is created by
								the framework when the object is stored
								the first time.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry spanname="element">name</entry>

							<entry spanname="desc">
								The name of the User.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry spanname="element">login-name</entry>

							<entry spanname="desc">
								An unique login name for the
								UserAccount.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry spanname="element">active</entry>

							<entry spanname="desc">
								A flag indicating if the UserAccount is
								active or has been deactivated. The
								initial state of a new UserAccount is
								active. It may be changed by using the
								activate or deactivate methods, only.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry spanname="element">person</entry>

							<entry spanname="desc">
								A link to the person resource that
								represents the user, too.
								<para>
									As this is not needed in the first
									release, it will be an empty
									element.
								</para>
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry spanname="element">
								creation-date
							</entry>

							<entry spanname="desc">
								This date is created by the framework
								when the framework stores the object the
								first time.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry spanname="element">creator</entry>

							<entry spanname="desc">
								Link to the user who created the object,
								the framework adds this element.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry spanname="element">
								modified-by
							</entry>

							<entry spanname="desc">
								Link to the user who modified the object
								the last time, the framework adds this
								element.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry spanname="element">
								last-modification-date
							</entry>

							<entry spanname="desc">
								This date is updated whenever the
								UserAccount is stored.
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Grant</title>
			<table frame="all">
				<title>Elements of Grant</title>
				<tgroup cols="17" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
					<colspec colname="c1" />
					<colspec colname="c2" />
					<colspec colname="c3" />
					<colspec colname="c4" />
					<colspec colname="c5" />
					<colspec colname="c6" />
					<colspec colname="c7" />
					<colspec colname="c8" />
					<colspec colname="c9" />
					<colspec colname="c10" />
					<colspec colname="c11" />
					<colspec colname="c12" />
					<colspec colname="c13" />
					<colspec colname="c14" />
					<colspec colname="c15" />
					<colspec colname="c16" />
					<colspec colname="c17" />
					<spanspec spanname="element" namest="c1"
						nameend="c4" align="left" />
					<spanspec spanname="desc" namest="c5" nameend="c17"
						align="left" />
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry spanname="element">Element</entry>

							<entry spanname="desc">Desription</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry spanname="element">granted-to</entry>

                            <entry spanname="desc">
                                Link to the resource (user-account or user-group)
                                the role is granted to by the Grant object.
                            </entry>
                        </row>
						<row>
							<entry spanname="element">role</entry>

							<entry spanname="desc">
								Link to the role that is granted to the
								user/group by the Grant object.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry spanname="element">assigned-on</entry>

							<entry spanname="desc">
								Link to the object for that a limited
								role is granted to the user/group by the Grant
								object.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry spanname="element">
								creation-date
							</entry>

							<entry spanname="desc">
								The date the role has been granted to
								the user/group. This is created by the
								framework when the framework stores the
								grant.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry spanname="element">created-by</entry>

							<entry spanname="desc">
								Link to the user who created the object,
								the framework adds this element.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry spanname="element">
								grant-remark
							</entry>

							<entry spanname="desc">
								Remark added during creation of the
								grant.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry spanname="element">
								revocation-date
							</entry>

							<entry spanname="desc">
								The date the grant has been revoked from
								the user. This is created by the
								framework when the revokeGrant method is
								executed.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry spanname="element">revoked-by</entry>

							<entry spanname="desc">
								Link to the user who revoked the
								object.The framework adds this element
								when the revokeGrant method is executed.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry spanname="element">
								revocation-remark
							</entry>

							<entry spanname="desc">
								Remark added during revocation of the
								Grant.
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
		</section>
	</section>
</chapter>
