<chapter>
	<title>User Management (AA)</title>
	<section>
		<title>Related Documents</title>
		<para>
			A detailed concept for User Management in eSciDoc can be
			found in
			<xref linkend="TTe06" />
			.
		</para>
		<para>
			The user management is closely related to the Concept for
			Authentication and Authorization
			<xref linkend="TTe06-1" />
			.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Overview of User Management (AA)</title>
        <para> For the first release, the User Management (AA) offers services in
            the following areas: </para>
		<itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">
						Caching of User Data:
					</emphasis>
				</para>
				<para>
					The eSciDoc users are represented within the system
					by User account objects. These user account objects
					can be seen as proxies that cache the information
					about the users provided by an external user
					management, e.g. provided by a Shibboleth Identity
					Provider or an LDAP server.
				</para>
				<para>
					An user account object can be identified by its
					internal id or by a temporarily valid
					esciDocUserHandle that is generated during the login
					process of the user. The latter is used to
					authenticate the user while handling incoming
					requests.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">
						Granting Roles to Users:
					</emphasis>
				</para>
				<para>
					The authorization in eSciDoc is based on roles that
					are granted to users. In most cases, granting a role
					to a user is limited to specific objects.
				</para>
				<para>
					The information about the granted roles and, in case
					of the limited roles, for which objects they have
					been granted to the user is stored within the User
					Management (AA).
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="bold">
						Embedding external user management:
					</emphasis>
				</para>
				<para>
					The external user management is responsible for
					authenticating a user and for providing the user's
					attribute to eSciDoc. It may be e.g. a Shibboleth
					Identity Provider or an LDAP server.
				</para>
				<para>
					The external user management is integrated within
					eSciDoc by an User Management Wrapper. This wrapper
					provides a service for the user login, encapsulates
					the communication with the external user management
					to authenticate the user and retrieve the user's
					attributes, and creates or updates the user proxy
					within eSciDoc. In case of successful user
					authentication it provides an eSciDocUserHandle that
					is used for identifying the User while authorizing
					an incoming request to an eSciDoc resource.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
	<section >
		<title>Supported resources</title>
		<para>
			For the first release, the User Management (AA) supports the
			following resources and subresources:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
			<listitem>
				<para>UserAccount</para>
				<itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
					<listitem>
						<para>Subresource Grants</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Subresource Grant</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>User Management Wrapper</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
</chapter>
